A Finding Aid to the Albert Duveen Collection of Artists' Letters and Ephemera, 1807-1946, in the Archives of American Art AAA.duvealbe
Archives of American Art
Albert Duveen collection of artists' letters and ephemera
1807-1946
AAA.duvealbe
Archives of American Art
1.1 Linear feet
The Albert Duveen collection of artists' letters and ephemera measures 1.1 linear feet and dates from 1807 to 1946. Unrelated letters written by over 170 mostly 19th and early 20th century American artists are found in this compiled collection of art critic, dealer, and collector Albert Duveen. Additional ephemera includes printed material and photographs of artwork.
Duveen, Albert
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Albert Duveen collection of artists' letters and ephemera was purchased from Duveen by the Archives of American Art in February 1956.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives holds a microfilm copy of the Albert Duveen art reference files and a lecture, "An Art Dealer is Intrigued by American Folk Art," delivered by Albert Duveen, March 4, 1961.
Existence and Location of Copies note
This collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reels DDU1, D9, D10, and NDU-1-5 at the Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Art critic, collector, and dealer Albert Duveen (1892-1965) lived and worked in New York City, New York. He is known for his expertise in early American art and was a cousin to Joseph Duveen, president of Duveen Brothers art dealers.
Scope and Contents note
The Albert Duveen collection of artists' letters and ephemera measures 1.1 linear feet and dates from 1807 to 1946. Unrelated letters written by over 170 mostly 19th and early 20th century American artists are found in this compiled collection of art critic, dealer, and collector Albert Duveen. Additional ephemera includes printed material and photographs of artwork.
Found are letters from artists Albert Bierstadt, Frederic E. Church, Frederick S. Church, Henry Inman, Constant Mayer, Jervis McEntee, Henry Mosler, Frederick Law Olmstead, Rembrandt Peale, Albert Rosenthal, and many others. Printed materials include catalog inventories of public and private art collections. There are also brochure booklets on New England historical houses and towns. Photographs are duplicate copies of early American artwork from Duveen's personal reference files.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 3 series.
Series 1: Letters, 1808-1910 (0.8 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Printed material, circa 1909-1946 (4 folders; Box 1, OV 2)
Series 3: Photographs, circa 1808-1910 (3 folders; Box 1)
Bierstadt, Albert, 1830-1902; Church, Frederic Edwin, 1826-1900; Church, Frederick S. (Frederick Stuart), 1842-1924; Inman, Henry, 1801-1846; Mayer, Constant, 1829-1911; McEntee, Jervis, 1828-1891; Mosler, Henry; Olmsted, Frederick Law, 1822-1903; Peale, Rembrandt, 1778-1860; Rosenthal, Albert, 1863-1939; Artists--United States; Collectors and collecting
- Letters, 1808-1910; Series 1; 0.8 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Letters are written by over 170 early American artists, including Albert Bierstadt, Frederic E. Church, Frederick S. Church, Constant Mayer, Henry Mosler, Frederick Law Olmsted, Albert Rosenthal, and Anne Whitney. Two letters of interest by Henry Inman and Rembrandt Peale describe opinions on their work and the works of others. There are also letters related to the John Trumbull estate; miscellaneous printed items included with letters; and a selection of letters written by European artists.
  Arrangement note
  Letters are arranged alphabetically by surname followed by letters from foreign and miscellaneous artists.
  - Avery, Samuel Putnam, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Beckwith, Carroll, circa 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bierstadt, Albert, circa 1869-1893 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Blashfield, Edwin Howland, circa 1893 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bosworth, William Welles, circa 1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Boughton, George Henry, circa 1894-1900 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bridgman, Frederick Arthur, 1893-1900 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Buttre, John Chester, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Champney, James Wells, circa 1890-1895 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chapman, John Gadsby, 1834-1885 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Church, Frederic Edwin, circa 1864-1886 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Church, Frederick Stuart, circa 1882-1920 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cole, Timothy, 1915-1917 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Crane, Bruce, 1899-1900 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cropsey, Jasper Francis, 1855-1892 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Ezekiel, Sir Moses Jacob, 1910-1913 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Fairman, James, 1875-1876 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Fay, Gaston, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Feke, Robert, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Fenn, Henry, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fosdick, James William, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Fournier, Alexis Jean, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - French, Edwin Davis, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Gibson, William Hamilton, 1880-1893 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Gould, Thomas Ridgeway, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Greatorex, Eliza, circa 1874 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Greenough, Horatio, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Gregory, Frank M., 1882 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Grosvenor, Thelma C., circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Hartley, Jonathan Scott, 1895-1903 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Hays, William Jacob, Sr., 1859 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Heade, Martin Johnson, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Healy, George P.A., circa 1891 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Hennessy, William John, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Herrick, H.W., 1876 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Herter, Albert, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hill, J. Henry, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Hillern, Bertha, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Huntley, Samantha L., 1909 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Inman, Henry, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Kappes, Alfred, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Kaufmann, Theodore, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Keith, Dora Wheeler, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Kitchell, Joseph Gray, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Knight, Daniel Ridgway, circa 1911-1922 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - La Farge, John, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Lambdin, James Reid, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Lanman, Abigail Trumbull, 1807-1844 (Box 1, Folder 50-53)
    Includes material on John Trumbull and the Trumbull estate.
  - Leslie, Charles R., circa 1815-1851 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Leutze, Emanuel, 1852-1864 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Lie, Jonas, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Linen, George, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Lippincott, William Henry, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Lock, Frederick W., 1849 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Longacre, James Barton, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Longpré, Paul, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Low, Mary Fairchild, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Low, Will Hicox, 1877-1909 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Lumley, Arthur, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Lupton, Thomas Goff, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - MacDonald, James Wilson, 1872-1886 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Matthews, William, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Mayer, Constant, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 68-69)
  - Mayer, Frank Blackwell, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - McArthur, John, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - McCord, George Herbert, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - McCutcheon, John Tinney, circa 1903 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - McEntee, Jervis, 1845-1888 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - McKenzie, Robert Tait, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Middleton, Stanley Grant, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Mignot, Louis Remy, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Miller, Alfred Jacob, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Millet, Francis Davis, circa 1884-1912 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Moran, Edward, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Moran, Peter, 1877-1901 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Morgan, Matthew, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Mosler, Henry, circa 1880-1903 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Mowbray, Harry Siddons, circa 1893 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Muller, Karl, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Mulvany, John, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - O'Connor, Andrew, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Oertel, Johannes Adam Simon, 1858-1905 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Olmstead, Frederick Law, 1862-1890 (Box 1, Folder 89-90)
  - Opper, Frederick Burr, 1901-1917 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Page, Fred B., 1846 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Page, William, 1852-1871 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Palmer, Erastus D., 1847-1885 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Palmer, John E., circa 1873 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Palmer, Walter Launt, 1899-1908 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Paris, Walter, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Parrish, Randall, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Partridge, William Ordway, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Pease, Joseph Ives, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Peixotto, Ernest C., 1930 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Perry, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Persico, Luigi, 1836-1844 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Pfeiffer, Emily, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Pike, William, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - Powell, William Henry, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - Powers, Hiram, 1844-1873 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - Raffaelli, Jean Francios, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Ranger, Henry Ward, 1893-1901 (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - Reid, Robert, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Rhead, Louis John, circa 1888-1893 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Richards, Thomas Addison, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Ripley, Robert Leroy, circa 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Robbins, Horace Wolcott, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Robinson, Anna, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - Robinson, Theodore, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Rogers, John, circa 1862-1871 (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - Rogers, Randolph, 1863-1874 (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - Rogers, William Allen, 1889-1928 (Box 1, Folder 119)
  - Rosenthal, Albert, 1886-1913 (Box 1, Folder 120)
  - Rossiter, Thomas Pritchard, 1860-1863 (Box 1, Folder 121)
  - Rothermel, Peter Frederick, 1873-1886 (Box 1, Folder 122)
  - Ruckstuhl, Frederic Wellington, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 123)
  - Saint-Gaudens, Augustus, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 124)
  - Sanderson, Charles Wesley, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 125)
  - Sarony, Napoleon, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 126)
  - Satterlee, Walter, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 127)
  - Schoff, Stephen Alonzo, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 128)
  - Scott, Emily Maria Spaford, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 129)
  - Selinger, Jean Paul, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 130)
  - Shattuck, Aaron Draper, circa 1856 (Box 1, Folder 131)
  - Smillie, George Henry, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 132)
  - Snell, Henry Bayley, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 133)
  - Sonntag, William Louis, 1860-1886 (Box 1, Folder 134)
  - Sterner, Albert Edward, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 135)
  - Stetson, Charles Walter, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 136)
  - Stewart, Julius L., 1888 (Box 1, Folder 137)
  - Stone, Horatio, 1856-1860 (Box 1, Folder 138)
  - Story, George Henry, 1887-1903 (Box 1, Folder 139)
  - Story, William Wetmore, circa 1879-1883 (Box 1, Folder 140)
  - Stout, James Varick, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 141)
  - Strother, David Hunter, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 142)
  - Taft, Lorado, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 143)
  - Tait, Arthur Fitzwilliam, 1855-1890 (Box 1, Folder 144)
  - Taylor, Henry Fitch, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 145)
  - Thompson, Charles A., circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 146)
  - Thompson, Laun't, circa 1864 (Box 1, Folder 147)
  - Thulstrup, Thure, 1885-1886 (Box 1, Folder 148)
  - Tilton, John Rollin, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 149)
  - Turcas, Jules, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 150)
  - Turner, Charles Yardley, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 151)
  - Turner, Ross Sterling, 1878-1886 (Box 1, Folder 152)
  - Valentine, Edward Virginius, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 153)
  - Van Boskerck, Robert Ward, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 154)
  - Van Elten, Hendrick Dirk Kruseman, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 155)
  - Van Laer, Alexander Theobald, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 156)
  - Volk, Douglas, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 157)
  - Volkmar, Charles, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 158)
  - Vos, J. Hubert, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 159)
  - Walcutt, William, 1851-1853 (Box 1, Folder 160)
  - Waldon, Lionel, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 161)
  - Walker, James, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 162)
  - Walter, Thomas Ustick, 1844-1885 (Box 1, Folder 163)
  - Waterman, Marcus, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 164)
  - Waugh, Ida, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 165)
  - Weeks, Edwin Lord, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 166)
  - Weir, Harrison William, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 167)
  - Weir, Robert Walter, 1835-1869 (Box 1, Folder 168)
  - White, G. Harlow, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 169)
  - Whitman, Sarah de St. Prix, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 170)
  - Whitney, Anne, circa 1878-1914 (Box 1, Folder 171)
  - Whittemore, William John, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 172)
  - Whittredge, Worthington, 1862-1908 (Box 1, Folder 173)
  - Wiggins, Carleton, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 174)
  - Wiles, Irving Ramsay, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 175)
  - Williams, George Alfred, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 176)
  - Wilmarth, Lemuel Everett, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 177)
  - Winterburn, George T., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 178)
  - Worth, Thomas, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 179)
  - Wust, Alexander, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 180)
  - Yewell, George Henry, 1874-1895 (Box 1, Folder 181)
  - Zilcken, Charles Louis Philippe, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 182)
  - Zimmerman, Eugène, 1896-1902 (Box 1, Folder 183)
  - Foreign Artists, circa 1814-1908 (Box 1, Folder 184-186)
  - Miscellaneous A-G, 1845-1891 (Box 1, Folder 187)
  - Miscellaneous H-L, circa 1817-1929 (Box 1, Folder 188)
  - Miscellaneous M-O, circa 1886-1925 (Box 1, Folder 189)
  - Miscellaneous P-S, circa 1867-1892 (Box 1, Folder 190)
  - Miscellaneous T-V, 1860-1891 (Box 1, Folder 191)
  - Miscellaneous W, circa 1858-1910 (Box 1, Folder 192)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1847-1914 (Box 1, Folder 193)
  - Miscellaneous Letters and Items, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 194)
- Printed Material, circa 1909-1946; Series 2; 4 Folders Box 1, OV 2
  Printed materials include catalog inventories of the following public and private art collections: the Bucks County Historical Society, the Lee Museum, J. Horace Harding, William Penn, and George Taylor. There are also brochure booklets on the historical towns of Cooperstown, Greenfield Village, South Haven, Yorktown, and Gloucester.
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1909-1946 (Box 1, Folder 195-197)
  - Print of Black Stallion, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 198)
    Oversized material housed in OV 2.
  - Oversize Print of Black Stallion from Box 1, Folder 198, circa 1808-1910 (Box OV 2)
- Photographs, circa 1808-1910; Series 3; 3 Folders Box 1
  Photographs are duplicate copies of early American artwork from Duveen's personal reference files. These include portraits, cityscapes, landscapes, still lifes, and abstract paintings.
  Materials are arranged by subject matter.
  - Duplicates From Duveen's Reference Files, circa 1808-1910 (Box 1, Folder 199-201)